Hello. My friend Jacques Becker
recreated a true story in all its detail.
My story. It took place in 1947
at the Santé prison
Face front!
Go ahead.
Let him go in right away. I'm in a rush.
Stand here!
Maurice Gaillarbois, 32 yrs. Old.
Block 13, cell 35.
The inmate has been refusing
to eat for 48 hours.
Why are you on
a hunger strike?
I'm innocent!
You'll have a fair trial if you're innocent.
Meanwhile, eat.
I don't want to eat, and I want
the judge to know I'm not eating
because if I don't eat,
it's his fault!
Okay, but the judge is eating.
And knowing you don't eat
won't lessen his appetite.
I won't eat!
Okay, we'll tell him
you won't eat.
Next!
What's this?
Gaspard, Claude, No. 6028.
Hid a lighter, supposedly gold plated.
You know very well
lighters are forbidden here.
Even without fuel, sir?
Even without fuel.
Strict regulations.
Someone must have told you
when you first got here.
Actually I forgot
it was in my pocket.
- And then you found it.
- That's right
Why didn't you give it
to a guard?
It would be returned to you
upon your release.
You're right, sir, but this
lighter has sentimental value.
I like to look at it
now and again.
- You say it's made of gold?
- Yes, sir.
That's a valuable.
It will be returned to you.
You deserve two weeks of mail-holding,
but I'll turn a blind eye this time.
Thank you very much, sir.
Nice guy!
You'll get your lighter
when you get out.
- Here's a new inmate!
- We're four already.
- So now you're five.
- We're expecting work.
We're getting cardboard to make boxes,
it'll take up a lot of room.
No one's forcing you!
In custody, work is voluntary.
- You don't like us working?
- Don't be a smart ass!
We have a right to work
if we want to.
I said, here's a new guy,
no arguments.
I'll argue.
We're already four in here
on top of the work we've
been waiting for.
Put down your stuff here,
and you, shut up!
- I'm being polite, sir!
- Let it go, Manu. That's the way it is.
Damn straight!
We'll bring you
a mattress later.
Sorry, I didn't ask
to come here.
Don't worry.
My name's Vosselin, but you can call me
Monseigneur. It's my nickname.
I'm Claude Gaspard.
I was in Block 8.
- But they moved us due to repairs.
- You'll be okay here.
- It doesn't feel that way.
- I said don't worry about that!
Let's not start again.
What's done is done.
- Roland Darbant.
- Hi!
That's Geo Cassid.
He's new. Moved from Block 8
on account of repairs.
- Hi!
- Hello.
Manu Borelli.
You'll be okay here.
Bring your bag.
Don't worry.
We'll put your stuff away.
Put it on the bed.
- Got a wardrobe at home?
- Yeah, why?
Everyone has a wardrobe,
and a wife too.
Got a wife?
Don't answer him.
You don't have to talk about yourself.
I don't mind talking about it.
Things all right with your woman?
No, I love someone else.
- Was she a good lover, the other one?
- Geo, leave us alone, will you?
Why? It's nice to talk about love,
it's healthy.
You see,
Geo is interested in love.
Women are interested in it too,
don't forget!
He's a specialist.
Much in demand.
Would you believe he had to hide
when he wanted to sleep alone!
Hey guys. We brought you work.
Let's go!
What spirit!
That won't last long.
We get bored in here!
You're gonna make me bawl.
- We brought you 5,000 sheets.
- We can count on you.
- What luck, eh?
- Go ahead and laugh, I mean it.
Sure, you won't even have time to eat.
Well, good luck!
Good night.
He's right,
this is a hell of a job!
It'll be good for us.
You hear, Geo?
Lazybones!
He'll get to it.
Come on, Manu!
- Do you mind?
- Go ahead.
Funny, I'm beginning
to like it.
You all asked to work
or just you three?
- All of us.
- You have to get to work.
You promised, Geo.
Wait, not yet.
There's the soup trolley.
- What's this?
- Chef's vermicelli special.
You're all dirtbags in the kitchen!
- You know, I...
- It's not his fault.
I said they're dirtbags.
Personal opinion, right?
It's not edible.
It looks foul.
Disgusting.
I won't insist.
- Not all that bad.
- You're always hungry.
Here, help yourselves!
There's enough for everyone.
You're nice, but we
have all we need!
Pack up your food;
you're our guest.
Your little mistress
spoils you.
Don't answer him
and sit down.
That's good.
It's disgusting.
Here, eat. Help yourself.
Goose liver!
You don't mess around.
Yes, look honey,
strawberry jam with real fruit,
chestnut spread.
Manu likes chestnut spread!
And I thought you all needed money.
- Because of this stuff?
- Well, yes.
Normally the only guys who work
are strapped for cash.
There are those who are bored too.
That's true, in cells where
they don't get along. Not here.
You'll never get me to believe
this is why you wanted to work.
So? What do you believe?
I don't know.
I'm surprised you do, that's all.
- Really?
- Yes, really.
Tell us about your mistress.
That'll keep you from talking crap.
May I have the spoon please?
- You share everything?
- As you see.
That's marvellous. I'm glad
I'm here with you guys.
The pleasure is all ours.
I can never tell whether
he's kidding or not.
That's my charm.
Have some, don't be shy.
All right. If you'll share
whatever I get.
You're a good man.
We're glad to have you.
A little cigarette to top it off.
Thanks.
And Manu?
Manu doesn't smoke.
- Gaspard, Claude?
- That's me.
There's a package for you
in your old block.
Hold it.
You look pleased,
all of a sudden. Why?
I like the new guy.
Yes, you can go.
Manu, we have to decide.
Do we tell him or not?
We tell him.
You're in charge. You decide.
Manu, we have to
tell the new guy.
You too?
Haven't got a choice.
We must start.
You should wait.
- Are you crazy?
- No.
I don't trust strangers,
and what a stranger!
- What do you know about him?
- You'll see.
So you'll wait to be tried,
sentenced to death and beheaded?
I have to deal with the courts, also.
Think of the others.
I don't give a shit
about the new guy, but
If it weren't him,
it'd be another.
And he could be a drag.
Gaspard, Claude,
Block 8 cell 26.
What? You're in
Block 11 cell 6?
Yes sir, I was in
Block 8 before.
- How come?
- My cell was changed.
I'll check that.
Gaspard, Claude, Block 11 cell 6.
That's right.
Smells good.
Looks like rice pudding...
Must be, boss.
Enjoy it! Next!
- I see Geo's at it.
- You see well.
I got some nice stuff.
Chitterling sausage, smoked fish.
Vanilla rice pudding.
- From your sweetheart.
- Exactly.
Who likes rice pudding?
Me, but I'm not hungry now.
- What's going on?
- Nothing, why?
I don't know,
I have this feeling.
While you were getting your package,
we talked about you.
We're used to living here together,
the four of us
and then you arrive,
so naturally we talk about you.
Sorry, Manu wanted to say something.
I'd like to hear it.
- We don't know you, nor you us.
- That's right.
But we took you in right away.
You're very kind.
And without knowing it you've
landed in a cell that's a bit special.
We're not all here
for the same reason.
But in court, the luckiest
will get 10 years.
As you see, my friends
and I risk a great deal.
You do.
So we'd like to know what
you're up against, Gaspard.
I'm accused of attempted
first degree murder.
That could get him 10 years easy.
Do you mind...
Who's charging you?
- My wife. One evening, at our Neuilly home.
- Congrats!
Shut up, Monseigneur! Go on.
I was with my wife
and her sister.
We were arguing
and my wife threatened me
with a shotgun.
I wanted to take it from her
but it went off
and she was wounded in the shoulder.
Says you. But your wife must tell
a different story since you're here.
My wife claims it was I who
drew the gun to shoot her.
She was angry with you, eh!
How old is your wife?
Thirty. 3 years older than me.
- And your sister-in-law?
- She's a kid. Seventeen.
- Was she there?
- Yes. She backed my testimony.
But hers was ruined
by a servant.
Bitch!
A woman who hates me.
She told the judge
Nicole was upstairs with her.
You say attempted first degree murder.
Why first degree?
There were 3 shotguns in the
gun-rack, only 1 was loaded.
What were you arguing about?
Money. In principal, anyway.
- Does Nicole screw well?
- What?
See, he screws.
Geo, that's enough!
Were they regular lead
or buckshot?
- Regular.
- Less fatal. Pity.
- What happened to your wife?
- Nothing serious.
Her left shoulder was hit.
She's just having a bit
of a hard time right now.
And she accuses you of wanting
to kill her. That's harsh!
What can you do?
You loaded the gun?
Is your wife rich?
Rich enough.
What's your official income?
That's all that counts in court.
I sold automobiles.
In other words, you lived
off your wife's money.
I guess.
You'll get
20 years hard labor.
- You think so?
- At least.
Are you sure?
Your case stinks. You wound
your wife who supports you.
You sleep with her sister.
You sell used cars.
The judges can't
stand that.
20 years labor
is a long time.
What's the matter with you?
We wanted to know
what you're risking.
Because we risk a great deal
waiting here quietly for appeal.
What?
We're going to escape.
- From here?
- From here.
You think we're crazy?
No, not at all.
Go on, Roland,
tell him all about it.
He knows what he's doing.
He's already escaped
three times; right Roland?
When I think that if I hadn't changed cells
I wouldn't be going with you.
I'm lucky!
As long as you trust us, you're lucky.
So when do we start?
It's gonna be lights out soon.
We can't dig the hole at night.
We have to take advantage
of the daily noises outside.
Of course!
Tonight we'll feast,
pass me that rice pudding.
Give me the box, Roland.
We'll share everything.
Dinner's served!
Funny how you rub your
hands together. Suits you.
Sure, I come from
a long line of clergymen.
My uncle was a bishop.
No kidding. I was wondering
about your name, Monseigneur.
- Well, I'm going for it.
- Be my guest!
Here we do nothing but eat.
What's the matter?
Nothing. I was thinking about
my grandmother. She raised me.
Was she rich?
Bloody Gaspard,
you were a happy kid.
Yeah, I had everything
I wanted.
You only mention your
grandmother. And your parents?
My mom died at my birth, my dad
5 years later in a car accident.
So you had no one
but your grandmother.
I also had paternal grandparents
who couldn't afford to keep me.
She's still alive,
your grandmother?
No, why?
So you're her heir.
You're rich?
I was, yes.
Pissed it all away. Then you met
a woman full of dough. Right?
My wife has money,
but that had nothing to do with it.
Don't be mad,
I'd have done the same thing.
Only if I'd married a rich woman
I wouldn't have shot her.
That's where you went wrong
You're starting to get
on our nerves, Monseigneur!
Never mind, no harm done.
You're getting on my nerves too
with your crap.
I want to sleep,
so shut up everybody. Got it?
Okay.
Emile!
Here, Mercier, you can finish up.
Slept well?
Feels weird to be here.
That always happens
when you change cells.
I was thinking about it all.
Didn't get much sleep.
Don't worry. Look,
they're sound asleep.
- Good morning.
- Good morning, Roland.
No one needs the doctor?
I don't think so.
Rise and shine!
Give us sugar and the cookies.
There.
Luckily, there's sugar.
Their coffee tastes like hell.
This one's nice.
Get all the glass slivers
so we don't cut ourselves.
One thing at a time.
- Who's the oldest here?
- Me.
Stay here. The others out.
Handkerchief.
All right.
That's all?
Next.
Your turn.
- Give me that.
- Hurry up!
All right.
Who pulled the chain?
I did. I'd never done it
from out here.
Quit horsing around.
Okay, move over.
Move.
Let's go!
You can get back in!
- They didn't spare us.
- Now everything's a mess.
On the contrary,
it's good for us.
- How's that?
- They won't be back too soon.
Put the stuff away,
I've got work to do.
You see, this little thing
acts as a periscope.
It's perfect. You see
the hall in both directions.
We've already had a search,
so we're okay on that front.
We can start digging today.
It's coming from No. 8.
- I'm listening.
- Package for No. 4. Ready?
Wait!
Tell them we're waiting for masons and
we can't send anything until further notice.
Swing!
Ready, No. 4?
Send it over.
Listen, no more packages today.
We're waiting for the masons.
- Did you hear that, No. 8?
- All right, thank you.
That way we'll have
some peace.
Let's go.
Who's the lookout?
Me, if you want.
Okay. But stay sharp,
tell us everything you see.
You can count on me.
Go on working, I don't
need you right now.
- Someone's coming.
- What?
- Some guys with blankets.
- Screw it. It's not for us.
Let me see.
It's heavy; you wouldn't think it.
It will do.
Geo, come on!
Move!
It'll take too much time.
You have to hit harder!
I think you're right.
No other way.
In one hour either we break
through or get caught.
You're crazy, it's impossible!
If anything saves us,
it'll be the noise.
They're here.
They moved along.
Your turn, Geo.
Monseigneur, it's no use
looking out, you know.
Are you crazy? Why?
If they come now
we'd be fried anyway.
What's wrong with you?
Can't see a thing.
Give me some cardboard.
We're there.
We go down tonight.
May I?
Now you've seen, move it,
we have to throw it all in.
Let's try.
Well?
Not bad.
Try to pull the string more lightly.
I'd like to, but you see,
it works one way and not the other.
Don't pull so hard.
Roland, closing time.
Gentlemen, closing time.
Clean up before you go to sleep.
All right.
We have 15 minutes
before the first round.
He's coming.
Get in bed quick.
Let's go!
He was early, damn it!
- Alright?
- Okay. Come down.
Monseigneur, take the string
and rock.
Okay?
That's an underground chamber
like this one.
That's the large cellar.
Why is it lit?
Listen.
It's deserted.
At night, except for the
patrol, no one comes here.
I'll cut this bar,
that'll do.
What if guards come by
and hear us?
I'll file 20 times,
and stop to listen.
And so on.
Finish it!
Let's go.
That's a corridor.
There's so much stuff down here.
This is where they store
their material.
The patrol must come down here
Another corridor.
They punch in.
See that one? I'll cut here
and make a master key.
Her husband sold
rabbit furs.
Another trade that's
disappeared.
She was beautiful.
There.
One day the guy caught us.
What a mess!
Really!
I thought we'd fight it out
but nothing happened.
He turned around
and left us there.
- And then?
- Well... then.
I saw the chick 2-3 times
and then got posted to Paris.
So obviously I stopped
seeing her.
They left through there.
We'll do the same.
Where are we going?
Look.
This is the rough map
of the prison basement.
We came from here.
At every corner of the prison
there's a similar room,
all interconnected.
By corridors like this one.
I see. But where is
the sewer shaft?
Maybe in one of the halls.
Maybe in the corridors.
Maybe there are several.
They have only
one type of lock.
Yes, like the cell doors.
So guards don't need 100 keys.
Give me some more light.
There!
Look at this animal.
Here comes your snack, baby!
Look!
See you soon.
What the hell were
they talking about?
I didn't understand
a word they said.
Look.
That's the door to the well.
Only this is a
damn spring lock.
- What are you doing?
- I'll file the hinges
- The door won't hold.
- Let me do it!
They check it, look.
They won't notice.
Fantastic!
Give me a hinge.
Give me the other one.
And now?
You'll see.
All right?
All right.
This way, we'll know if they
came through while we were below.
Your turn.
It works.
This is concrete. No use trying.
Let's check the other one.
Think they come
down here often?
Just the sewage workers,
and probably not often.
- They've got us trapped.
- Is it that hard?
See for yourself.
That's not concrete,
it's cheap cement. It'll give.
What do you mean?
This is right in the curve.
We'll dig a tunnel
around the plug.
- That'll take weeks.
- It's a matter of days.
We'll come back tomorrow with tools.
They came by.
Put the door back in place.
We didn't come this way.
It's shorter this way.
We've almost come full circle.
Tomorrow, this'll be our crowbar.
Just 5 more cells.
It won't work.
They already removed
the boards.
Hurry up, they're coming!
Coming!
Hurry up!
Come on, Roland!
Hurry!
Quick, the dummies!
Hello there!
Hello, sir!
They're all asleep
in there!
Gotta dream, sir!
You sleep fully dressed
these days?
I've always been
sensitive to the cold.
What happened to you?
You're already dressed.
How come?
Funny guy. We were getting ready
to go to the hole.
- Nothing like trust.
- Tell us what happened.
- We found a way out. Right?
- I believe so.
Why didn't you
come up earlier?
Do you have a watch? No!
Well, neither do we.
That can't go on.
Now let's try not to make
life difficult, shall we?
Life! You could say
she came at me full on.
The clap and the slammer at once.
That's a lot for one man, I tell you.
No women ever, kid!
That's the secret.
Well, to each his own.
Right doc?
No men either!
That's a good one!
So you manage alone?
Listen, you want
your face punched?
Forget it.
Let's see your nose!
Just a drop.
Thanks.
Whenever you want.
At your service.
Sir, please.
Arms up.
Stop playing games.
Why did you take sand?
To scour our bowls.
What's so wrong?
Gotta keep things clean
and since we have nothing...
Thanks, sir!
Exactly 30 minutes. Every half hour
we flip it upside-down, make a mark,
this way we can tell the time
and be safe.
Super!
The block is about three feet wide.
We'll have to dig a 10-foot tunnel.
Let's set up the boards.
Let's have them.
With this we're sure not
to block the grooves with debris.
Give me that one.
Let me see.
Say, you made a real key!
With this, the others can move
around the cellar without me.
Manu, it's 2 a.m.
Gotta get back.
The guards.
They just came by.
Hurry down. Roland's
waiting for you below.
What filth!
It's not easy, I tell you.
See you.
It's over there.
It's over there, Geo.
I just spent 28 minutes
to get you and come back.
- It's hard, I warn you.
- We do our best.
Good luck.
I better get some sleep.
Don't forget the time.
Remember the hourglass.
Go get some sleep.
He's incredible.
Yeah. Okay, I'll start.
- Manu, it's amazing.
- What?
I never experienced this.
What?
You might think it's strange
but it's the first time in
my life that I feel right.
I swear to you it's true.
It's great to be
with guys like you.
Yeah, I think I've changed.
I think it's because
of you and Roland.
What do they think down there?
It'll work, they'll manage
with the key as well as I do.
Say, Geo handles
the shaft door very well.
He managed
to replace it in one go.
I'd never have thought him capable.
Everything's okay in the hall.
I'm going to lie down.
He should go down too.
I'll take him tomorrow night.
Okay.
Get some sleep, you need it.
Thanks, Manu.
The faucet's leaking
more and more.
The joint's rotten.
It can burst at any time.
If that happens at night,
we'll have visitors.
Gotta take care of it right away.
Monseigneur, go knock.
It's a nuisance having
the plumbers here.
We have no choice.
You don't like workers,
do you?
Sleep, Geo, sleep!
Ah, this guy!
- Hello, sir!
- Well?
Our faucet's leaking.
Waste of water.
Great, they busted the faucet;
now I have to look for a plumber.
This one isn't dead, I hope?
We like you too much
to give you trouble.
If we wanted to die we'd wait
till you were off duty.
These guys are capable of suicide,
of anything really!
- Capable of the best too.
- Very well put.
You'd have made a good lawyer.
Okay, I'll send the plumbers in.
Meanwhile, get ready for your walk.
It's just about time.
Hello, sir!
Hello!
Hello, guys.
Try to fix this, and hurry!
- So it's leaking?
- See for yourself!
It's running day and night
and gets on our nerves.
Time for exercise!
Stupid jerk.
He's always in a hurry!
Time for your walk,
let's move it!
Behave yourselves on the way.
Exercise time.
Let's move.
Behave yourselves on the way.
Exercise time.
Let's get moving.
See, it stopped leaking.
Try not to break it again.
Thanks, sir.
Now we'll have some quiet.
They were surprisingly fast.
They didn't even wait
for their reward.
Yeah, that's strange.
Usually these guys beg.
That's it, they stole
my cigarettes.
Mine too, a whole new
pack of Gauloises.
They swiped my stamps,
two whole sets.
That's it, nothing more?
- No food missing.
- Nor here.
Lucky me, I don't think
they touched my stuff.
What're you doing?
Let it go!
It's not worth the trouble.
I think it is.
What now?
Sir, is M. Grinval here?
Yeah, I just ran into him. Why?
Do me a favor and ask him to stop by.
All right.
Who's Grinval?
Block Chief.
Hello, M. Grinval. Excuse us,
but here's what happened.
The plumbers were here
while we were out in the yard.
- And?
- They're smoking our cigarettes.
And mailing their letters home
with our stamps.
What were they doing here?
Our faucet was leaking.
This faucet's too tight now.
I'll be back with the plumbers.
Thank you, M. Grinval.
Now we'll get our exercise.
You asked for us, M. Grinval.
Come in.
Take a look at the faucet.
We just fixed it, M. Grinval.
See you!
Here buddy, have a smoke!
What do you want from us?
That's enough, Geo,
you're being vicious.
Search him.
Hand over the goods.
Assholes!
Next time, ask.
It'll be cheaper.
- Job done?
- Yes, M. Grinval. Thanks.
You may join the work team
in Block 3.
Yes, sir.
Let's go!
Everything all right?
Perfect, sir. Thank you.
Well, well...
I liked that.
Here are your smokes.
You really told 'em.
You were fantastic!
You got good paws, Geo.
You're not serious, Manu.
With all that's going on.
You're acting like a kid.
Whatever!
Roland, I'm not
leaving with you.
What?
I'm staying here.
You don't trust us any more?
On the contrary, I'm sure
you'll make it, that's why.
I don't know if I told you
but when I was arrested
my mother almost dropped dead.
If I escape, the police
will go to her again.
That could kill her,
so I'm staying.
I'm not telling
the others yet.
Let me have a drink.
It's going well,
we're not far any more.
Too bad you're not
coming with us.
I'm going to work.
You're okay?
We must be getting close,
it's getting hard again.
Geo!
Answer me! Geo!
There, he's awake.
Did you sleep well?
You're real dirty!
You must have really hit hard.
Sure did. Didn't we, Geo?
Next!
Hello, who? Gaspard, Claude?
He's right here.
I'll send him over.
Visiting room.
Lucky you!
Kiss her for me.
Gaspard, Claude.
No. 1.
- How'd you do it?
- Through the lawyer's secretary.
I manage. Not like you.
You can't even send a letter.
If I could only write you.
Tell me, you're still
staying at your sister's?
The house is just as much as mine
as it is hers. But we don't talk.
We eat in separate rooms.
She's still madly in love with you.
I hear her sobbing in bed at night.
If you would see her,
she'd come right away.
What makes you say that?
If you'd ask her yourself,
she'd withdraw charges.
That's not what the lawyer
told me last time.
He said she flatly refused.
She wants to punish us.
Listen, I've been thinking.
I'll go to England for a year.
It'll calm her down.
Why England?
To study English.
I always wanted to.
Nicole, if you knew how
much I want.
I want.
When you get out I'll come back.
Then we could...
And you, don't you want it?
You're so curious!
Don't play games, Nicole.
It annoys me.
You! Where are you going?
I'm going...
Sorry, Chief.
I made a mistake.
This is my old cell.
Let me see your pass.
You're from Block 11, right?
The other way.
I'd really like to put you in the hole.
- Let me explain, sir.
- What would you explain?
- Going to make a deal?
- I assure you it was a mistake.
What's going on?
Here's an inmate of Block 11
on his way back from a visit.
Instead of going back to his
own cell he came here.
I'm sorry, sir,
I was just going to explain.
I do belong to Block 11,
cell 6
but before that I was
in Block 8, cell 26.
You want the warden to believe
you suddenly lost your memory.
I'm sorry, that's exactly
what happened.
I was coming back from a visit,
and totally confused.
These things happen, don't they?
I know you, I think.
Yes, sir. I bothered you
about a trifle.
I kept a cigarette lighter,
a golden one
Oh, yes. What's your name?
Claude Gaspard, sir.
Yes. Go back to your cell
and in the future,
try to be more attentive.
Absolutely, sir. Thank you.
- Want some?
- No thank you, later.
Our friend isn't talkative.
Nor are you.
We haven't had a visit.
So you want the story.
No, just tell us if she's
a blond or a brunette.
Come on.
Yes, I just saw a woman.
That's what you wanted to know.
May I ask one question?
Just answer yes or no.
Ask away, I don't promise
anything.
After making love, does she
pick your blackheads?
Does she or doesn't she?
Shit.
- What a pleasant visit.
- Isn't it?
- You don't trust us, do you?
- I do, I do.
We know you're model inmates,
but we have our duties.
Good, because we
appreciate you.
- Really!
- Don't we?
Absolutely.
Anyway, I don't see why you came
suddenly like this.
We didn't mean to.
We've seen Freddy across the hall.
What did he do?
We're looking for a file
hidden in a desk blotter.
So?
I see you haven't got any
but you've got cardboard.
You could make one.
All we make here are boxes.
No desk blotter.
So did you find it?
Curious, aren't you?
Want to know everything.
You'll meet Freddy one day
and he'll tell you.
He must have been worried
when he saw you.
One always gets worried
when they see me.
You're kind to clean up.
Don't stand there, move!
Pierre!
Come on, we're off.
See you!
I thought we were done for.
Terrible!
We have to dig,
get through and piss off.
Tonight or tomorrow.
Otherwise we're screwed.
Gaspard!
What is it?
This is it, look.
We're on the other side.
My jacket.
Let's go!
There's an exit.
Come.
Come have a look.
Look at the prison.
Imagine!
A cab!
We could almost take it.
Listen!
6 o'clock.
Let's go get the others.
That's it, Roland!
- What?
- You won.
We got through, we were in
the main sewer, then in the streets.
The street?
Yes. Gaspard even wanted
to take a cab.
Tonight we'll be out of here.
Just a second.
- The youngest picks.
- Why me?
Because you're
the youngest. Pick.
- Monseigneur.
- Bravo, Monseigneur!
Good, the eldest will
lead the way.
Go ahead, pick another!
Go on!
Roland. And Gaspard.
You go last, kid,
but if you want my turn, it's okay.
- He'll take mine.
- Why? No reason for that.
- There is. I'm not going.
- What?
I'm not going.
Roland knows.
Since when?
Since I told him. I did work.
Did my share, okay?
We can't say anything.
You're old enough to do as you choose.
Yeah, I'm old enough.
Gaspard goes second
instead of Geo.
Hello! Are you Gaspard, Claude?
- Yes, why?
- Come with me.
- Where to?
- You'll see.
Take your jacket and
button your collar.
M. Grinval, where are you
taking him like that?
You're too curious, Borelli!
- Are you ready?
- Any time.
What does this mean?
It means that the director
just summoned him.
What's the occasion?
I don't know!
This way.
Gaspard, warden.
Thank you, Grinval.
Have a seat.
- Feeling good since yesterday?
- Very well, thank you.
You don't have a good sense
of direction, do you?
If it weren't for me, you'd have
ended up in the hole for a week.
- My apologies again, sir.
- You're very educated and nice.
- That helps in life.
- I haven't noticed.
I'll prove it to you.
I looked into your case
and found out something that
will interest you enormously.
What is it, sir?
- In a minute.
- Sorry.
Here is the charge against you.
Attempted first degree murder.
Actually I'm accused of wounding
my wife with a gunshot.
How did that happen?
Look, I'm not interrogating you.
That's not my line of duty.
This is a private conversation.
I know, sir,
and I appreciate it.
With your permission,
I'll tell you all about it.
Go ahead!
In two words, we had a fight,
my wife and I.
She threatened me with a shotgun.
I wanted to take it from her
but it went off
and she was wounded.
I wish it had been me.
Anyway, she recovered fast.
- As fast as that?
- She's in perfect shape.
So why didn't she
withdraw charges?
Because Committing Magistrate
M. Labourdette told her not to.
You see I'm not everyone's
cup of tea, sir.
- You think it's the magistrate?
- My attorney certainly does.
You believe a magistrate can
pressure a witness like that.
Especially a woman,
jealous and in love.
How do you know my
wife is in love?
Because she withdrew her
charges yesterday.
- So I'm going to be released.
- Probably.
As soon as the magistrate
dismisses the case.
Maybe not tomorrow,
but soon.
You don't seem very pleased.
What are you thinking about?
Tell me.
Perhaps I can help.
I'm coming, sir.
All right, back to your cell.
Yes, M. Grinval.
What are you waiting for?
Arms up!
Something incredible happened.
My wife withdrew her charges.
It is beyond me.
Can you imagine?
How do you know?
The warden just told me.
What do you think of that?
- So you're not coming with us?
- Of course I am.
- Are you crazy?
- Listen.
I know my story better
than you, no?
My wife backed off but I'm
still in for at least 5 years.
- What makes you think that?
- You told me yourself
that the court won't
like my story one bit.
For me not to go to court,
the magistrate has to dismiss the case.
Magistrate Labourdette
certainly won't do that.
The warden told you all this?
No. I know it just as
well as he does.
What the hell were you doing
in his office for 2 hours?
He's a nice guy. He's interested
in my case. That's all.
Right. That's why
he kept you for 2 hours.
He always does that!
Every day he summons an
inmate just to chat.
Did you have tea?
What are you saying?
Tell us what happened.
You went to see the warden.
He told you the good news
and then what? Tell us.
What's the matter with you?
Tell us what you told him.
Manu, you're crazy.
You think I betrayed you?
Is that it?
I believed you were my friend.
I'm sorry.
It's okay.
Guys, he's here.
Go!
They're already asleep?
That's right. I'm the only one
who works around here.
You're one to talk.
I swear!
All clear.
What a tie!
A piece of blanket
will always be a piece of blanket.
Go!
Bye, Geo.
Come on, Roland.
Manu.
God, don't!
Let go of me,
it's no use!
Undress them. Hurry.
Are you okay?
Do you need help?
Thank you, I'll manage.
It's all over.
They go into solitary confinement.
We're done here. Come out
the other way. It'll be easier.
Cell No. 7.
Poor Gaspard.
You have been watching
a film by Jacques Becker.
THE HOLE